Guide to the Records of the Office of the Treasurer (Leroy Elwood Kimball) RG.10.9
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Treasurer (Leroy Elwood Kimball)
1910-1963
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of the Treasurer
RG.10.9
3 Linear Feet in 6 boxes
This collection contains administrative records of NYU's Office of the Treasurer from 1910-1963, and is mainly comprised of records generated by Leroy Kimball who served in various financial positions with the University during the first half of the 20th century. The records are primarily financial, and include receipts, bills, invoices, leases, budgets and accompanying correspondence.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Administrative Papers of Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown 1900-1937
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains administrative and miscellaneous files generated during Leroy Kimball's tenure at New York University and following his retirement. The records were transferred from the Treasurer's office from Kimball Hall in 1991 by Fred Knauth and Muriel Mantel and consist of 6 Hollinger boxes comprising 3 linear feet. Ranging in date from 1910 to 1963, the records were in fairly good condition and in approximate chronological order when received. It was for this reason that they were not broken up into various series. The current arrangement is topical and in chronological order by subject.
The vast majority of these records are financial and include: receipts, bills, invoices, leases, budgets and their accompanying correspondence. The material originates from the following divisions or units: University Attorney's office, various schools and/or divisions, the Faculty Club, the First Avenue Association, the Council/Board of Trustees, Libraries, Hofstra College, Law Center, Medical Center, Bradley-Burgum Faculty Dismissal case, Hall of Fame and GPA Program with Syracuse University and the State University of New York. Worthy of particular note is the comprehensive file containing, clippings, correspondence, and other materials on the building of the Law School's Vanderbilt Hall in the 1950's and the accompanying protests and demonstrations regarding the evictions and demolition of residential property. In addition, there is a folder containing comprehensive correspondence and memorandums regarding NYU's agreement with Hofstra College in the 1920's and the subsequent dissolution of that agreement.
Historical/Biographical Note
Leroy Elwood Kimball retired from NYU in 1956 after 45 years as a financial officer of the University. Born in Flint, Michigan on October 31, 1888, he received his Bachelor's Degree from Albion College in 1910 and became City Editor of the Albion Evening Recorder in Michigan for one year before coming to NYU as an assistant Bursar in 1911. On June 17, 1914, he married Gipsy Robinson and received his Master's from NYU in 1917. During his tenure, he held the following positions: Assistant Bursar from 1911-1920, Bursar from 1920-1925, Comptroller from 1925-1945, and Vice Chancellor and Comptroller from 1945-1956.
In addition to the positions he held at NYU Kimball was very active in other matters. He was a trustee of the American Scenic & Historic Preservation Society and its president from 1933 to 1941. In 1937, Kimball was appointed by Governor Lehman to the New York State Commission to Survey Scenic, Historic and Commercial assets of the Hudson River valley. He was a member of the Advisory Committee of Historical and Patriotic Societies at the New York World's Fair of 1939, and in 1933, was the treasurer of the Association of American Colleges. Kimball belonged to the Andiron Club of New York, The Pilgrims, Phi Beta Kappa and other groups, was a trustee of Albion College and wrote numerous monographs. He made his home on Buckberg Mountain, Tomkins Cove-on-Hudson, New York and "Brooklands" in Surrey, England. In 1959, Kimball Hall was named in his honor.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Provenance
Papers were transferred from the Treasurer's office from Kimball Hall in 1991 by Fred Knauth and Muriel Mantel.
Administrative records.; Universities and colleges |z United States |x Administration.; New York (N.Y.).; Correspondence.; College trustees.; Syracuse University; State University of New York; New York University. Hall of Fame for Great Americans; New York University. School of Education; Andiron Club of New York City; Alexander, George, 1843-1930; New York University. School of Engineering and Science; Hofstra University; Kimball, LeRoy Ellwood, 1888-; Armstrong, George; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934; Kingsley, William; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963; New York University. College of Dentistry; New York University. Institute of Economic Affairs; New York University. Institute of Fine Arts; New York University. Law Center; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance; New York University. Libraries; New York University. Medical Center; New York University. Council
- Series I: Topical Files
  Scope and Contents note
  Arrangement is topical and in chronological order by subject.
  - Misc. Council & Attorney File, 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    bar code: 3 1142 04225451 9
  - Vice Chancellor for Development, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Institute of Fine Arts, 1924-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - School of Engineering, 1917-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - School of Pedagogy & Education, 1910-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Institute of Economic Affairs, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Club: University Attorney File, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Club: Pledges, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Club, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Club, 1941-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225452 7
  - Government House, 1915-1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Extramural Division, 1914-1931 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - First Avenue Association, 1927-1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - First Avenue Association, 1935-1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - GPA-Lavanburg Corner House, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - College of Dentistry, 1922-1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - College of Dentistry, 1929-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Council: Alterations to Council Room, 1938-1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Council: Portrait of Chancellor Brown, 1930-1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Council: Portrait of William Kingsley, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Council: Miscellaneous, 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Attorney Correspondence & Browsing Room, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wagner College Agreement, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Council: Portrait of Dr. George Alexander, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225453 5
  - Libraries: Adler Lectures on Emmet Collection, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Libraries: American Index Fund, 1928-1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Libraries: Brainerd Books, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Libraries: School of Commerce, Accounts & Finance Library, 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Libraries: Dean Balliet's Teachers Library, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Libraries: Director of Libraries, 1935-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Libraries: Law Library, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Libraries: Librarian, 1934-1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Libraries: NYU Film Library, 1940-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Libraries: Society for the Libraries, 1940-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Libraries: Peloubet Gift, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Libraries: University Heights Library - Attorney Files, 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Libraries: Warburg Gift - Friedsam House, 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Libraries: University Heights Library, 1918-1921 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Libraries: University Heights Library, 1922-1947 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Libraries: Henry Staudigal v. NYU from University Attorney's Files, 1931-1933 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Libraries: Washington Square Library, 1923-1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hofstra College from University Attorney's Files, 1935-1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225454 3
  - Hofstra College from University Attorney's Files, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - University Attorney's Files Re: Taxes, Titles, Leases & Mortgages, 1935-1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Law Center: Laying of Cornerstone, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Law Center: Eggers & Higgins Sketches, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Law Center: Equipment Purchased, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Law Center: Campaign Materials, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Law Center: Actions & Protests Re: Evictions and Demolition, 1945-1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Law Center: Building Campaign Publicity, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225455 0
  - Law Center: Building Campaign Publicity, 1947-1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kindergarten Training School, 1922-1924 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center: Medical School Miscellaneous, 1911-1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Medical Center: Demolition Ceremonies, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Medical Center: H. Stanley Hillyer Award, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Medical Center: "Medical Advance" (gaps), 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Medical Center: Vice Chancellor George Armstrong, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bradley - Burgum Faculty Dismissal Case, 1951-1954 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    bar code: 3 1142 04225456 8
  - Hall of Fame, 1920-1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Agreement with Syracuse University Re: Albany (?), 1949-1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - NYU - Syracuse University - State University Graduate School of Public Administration, 1949-1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Materials, Signature Page, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scholarships, 1919-1951 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    General